A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Lectures and Research Colloquia FA229
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Lectures and Research Colloquia
1972-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
FA229
1.68 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
Biographical/Historical note
Lectures, Seminars, Research Colloquia and Thesis Presentations all form an integral part of the educational program at The Rockefeller University. Lectures which report on the work of the speaker's laboratory were one of the methods. of interchange of information among the scientists, dating from the beginnings of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. At that time they were called Friday afternoon lectures and were important presentations. Over the years different patterns of arrangement developed. Between 1953-1968, when Detlev Bronk was President, Alfred E. Mirsky was in charge of arranging the lectures, followed by Victor Wilson and Paul Cranefield. In the academic year 1974/1975 a committee was established with direct responsibility for programming and scheduling.
The 1974/1975 committee is composed of: Samuel C. Silverstein, Chairman, Einar Gall, Secretary, Elizabeth Dickson, Martha Fedorko, George Miller, Norton Zinder.
From their beginning, Christmas Lectures were handled by Alfred E. Mirsky under terms of a grant to him. (See Alfred E. Mirsky papers).
University Lectures and Research Colloquia are usually held on a Friday afternoon at 3:45 P.M.
Seminars are not normally arranged by the Committee on Lectures.
1973/1974, Dr. Paul Cranefield, then chairman of the Committee on Lectures instituted a plan to record, on tape, the University Lectures.
Scope and Contents note
Consists of announcements (not including the Calendar of Events) starting in 1972, and audio tapes, where available, starting 1974, and some correspondence.
Box 1: Announcements/Release Forms Box 2: Audio Tapes
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 449
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
When requesting to view or listen to audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Related Materials
Also see:
Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, Alfred E. Mirsky Christmas Lectures, Tapes (FA876) Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, Audiovisual Materials, Lectures and Assorted Events (FA953)
Biology -- Research; Microbiology; Medicine, Preventive; Medical sciences; Medical research; Medical education; Physics; Biochemistry; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Life sciences; Science -- Study and teaching; Biophysics; Physical sciences; Sound recordings
- Mauzerall, David. Why Chlorophyll in Photosynthesis, 1973 October 19 (Box 1)
- Goldberger, M.L. (Princeton U.). Science and Life in China, 1973 December 7 (Box 1)
- Zinder, Norton D. The RNA Phages and What They've Told Us, 1973 December 20 (Box 1)
- Choppin, Purnell W. Viruses and Cell Membranes, 1974 January 4 (Box 1)
- Bajer, Andrew S. (University of Oregon). New Interpretations of Chromosome Movements (The Zipper Theory), 1974 February 8 (Box 1)
- Wilson, Victor J. The labyrinth, the Brain and Posture, 1974 February 15 (Box 1)
- Watson, James D. (Harvard University). The First Two Years of the National Cancer Advisory Board, 1974 April 5 (Box 1)
- Sir MacFarlane Burnet (University of Melbourne). Intrinsic mutogenesis in relation to aging and age-associated Disease, 1974 April 23 (Box 1)
- Mark Kac. Chance, Fluctuations and Order, 1973 September 28; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 62 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15275)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access copy available.
- Edelman, Gerald M. Signaling and Control at the Cell Surface, 1974 January 18; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 25 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15276)
- Ratliff, Floyd. The Logic of the Retina, 1974 March 15; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 69 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15277)
- Miller, George A. Psycholexicology, or the Dictionary in Our Heads, 1974 April 19; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 73 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15278)
- Kripke, Saul. What's in a Name? The Problem of Reference, 1974 May 15; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 124 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15279)
- James M. Manning. The Anti-Bacterial Action of β-chloro-d-alanine, 1974 January 11; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 43 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15280)
- Alexander Tomasz. The mode of enlargement and inheritance of the cell surface: Coordinated incorporation of glycopeptide and polysaccharide unites, 1974 November 15; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 81 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15281)
- Bruce Merrifield. The study of proteins through chemical synthesis, 1974 December 13; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 72 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15282)
- Richard M. Krause. Use of streptococcal antibodies to probe for mechanisms of antibody synthesis, 1975 January 17; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 66 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15283)
- Ian Gibbons. The structural basis of motility in sperm flagella, 1975 January 21; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 66 mimutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15284)
- Hiroshi Asanuma. Cerebral mechanisms controlling movement, 1975 February 14; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 60 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15285)
- Seymour Kety. Recent genetic and bio-chemical approaches to schizophrenia, 1975 March 6; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 97 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15286)
- Sheldon Segal. Evaluation of population control programs worldwide, 1975 March 7; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 78 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15287)
- Abraham Pais. Weak forces: How it began, 1975 April 4; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 70 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15288)
  Scope and Contents note
  Title originally announced as: History of the development of the concept of the electron Microscope.
- Bruce S. McEwen. Interactions of steroid hormones with the brain, 1975 May 2; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 55 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15289)
- Martin J., Klein. Albert Einstein: A portrait of the scientist as a young man, 1975 May 13; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 69 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15290)
- Hidesaburo Hanafusa. Virus-host interaction in Rous sarcoma virus infection, 1975 October 10; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 70 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15291)
- Walle J.H. Nauta. The changing concept of the Limbic system, 1975 October 16; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 91 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15292)
- Walter Stoeckenius. Light energy transduction in Halobacterium Halobium, 1975 October 24; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 67 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15293)
- John G. Nicholls. Modification and regeneration of synaptic connections in normal and cultured leech ganglia, 1975 November 3; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 85 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15294)
- Miklos Muller. Animal life without oxygen: Biochemical mechanisms, 1975 November 21; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 57 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15295)
- G.J.V. Nossal. Recent evidence favoring the clonal abortion theory of immunological tolerance, 1976 January 6; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 68 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15296)
- David Baltimore. What cells have terminal transferase?, 1976 January 9; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 58 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15297)
- Hans Bethe. The energy problem, 1976 January 23; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 79 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15298)
- S. Chandrasekhar. Black holes in astronomy and physics, 1976 February 20; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 85 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15299)
- E.G.D. Cohen. The quest for the absolute zero of temperature, 1976 April 9; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 62 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15300)
- George Palade. Blood capillaries revisited, 1976 May 7; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 88 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15301)
- Leland Hartwell. Control of cell division in yeast, 1976 October 15; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 64 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15302)
- Donald Griffin. Future prospects for a comparative psychology, 1976 November 5; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 78 minutes (Box 2, Reel AV 15303)